<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[IndieHosters]]></title>
  <link href="https://indiehosters.net/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://indiehosters.net/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-30T17:55:53+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://indiehosters.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[indiehosters]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[contact@indiehosters.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Start Page]]></title>
    <link href="https://indiehosters.net/blog/StartPage"/>
    <updated>2014-12-01T13:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://indiehosters.net/blog/StartPage</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="just-configuring">Just configuring</h2>

<p>Since we started, a lot of people are asking us how exactly IndieHosters is different from:</p>

<ul>
  <li>SandtStorm.io</li>
  <li>classic CMS hosting</li>
  <li>Cpanel</li>
  <li>..</li>
</ul>

<p>First of all, we want to state out loud, we are not writing software. Pieces of code you can find on <a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/">github/indiehosters</a> are mostly configuration and documentation.</p>

<p>IndieHosters is a network of Hosters that share an ideology and a migration format. We have now a “reference implementation” on how to run the migration format. But this implementation is just configuration of industry standard tools - namely CoreOS. (But tomorrow, we’ll also have ubuntu, and probably yours)</p>

<p>(Later we’ll publish more on the <a href="http://indiewebcamp.com/one_click_migration">migration format</a>)</p>

<h2 id="oh-wait">Oh wait!</h2>

<h3 id="how-can-the-users-control-their-applications">How can the users “control” their applications?</h3>

<p>This is indeed a good question. Some people made the choice to write software to solve this problem. We call it meta-software, software to manage software. There is already a bunch on the free software market:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://yunohost.org/">YunoHost</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://sandstorm.io/">Sandstorm</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://arkos.io/">arkos</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://freedomboxfoundation.org/">Freedom Box</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://cozy.io/">Cozy</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://owncloud.org/">ownCloud</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.webmin.com/">webmin</a></li>
</ul>

<p>And actually, we plan to offer hosting also for these in the future. One of the problems of these software products is they are aimed at technical people. And they all have some kind of technical restrictions:
- one VM/hardware per user
- one language for all the applications
- strong opinion on how to run the software</p>

<p>We plan to offer hosting at scale, on shared resources, and in an easy way.</p>

<h2 id="introducing-the-startpage">Introducing the StartPage</h2>

<h3 id="socket-activation">Socket activation</h3>

<p>One of the ideas we have in mind is to use <a href="http://www.freedesktop.org/software/systemd/man/systemd.socket.html">Socket Activation</a>. For the non technical people, it means that for a user, all the applications we offer will be available from the first registration. And just during the first connection to the application, the software will be started.</p>

<p>So at the end, the start page is basically a static html page with links to the different applications.</p>

<p>We are still at the planning phase, and we have to benchmark this technique, but we are really enthusiastic about this idea.</p>

<h3 id="migration-button">Migration button</h3>

<p>Then for every application, there will be a migration button that will allow you to migrate from one Hoster to another. We believe that this is really our value added for the customer to be able to migrate. It’s getting closer and closer to the feeling of freedom you could have in the time your data were on your computer.</p>

<h3 id="indieweb-use-case">IndieWeb use case</h3>

<p>Let’s take the IndieWeb application that we are currently hosting for alpha users and <a href="https://www.indiegogo.com/projects/indiehosters/x/9169969">offering as a pre-sale</a>. Being part of the IndieWeb, is basically having your domain name with a blogging platform.</p>

<p>The plan for registration is:</p>

<ul>
  <li>get an IndieHoster based on your language</li>
  <li>connect with email/google/facebook/twitter</li>
  <li>choose your domaine name (guessed on your connection)</li>
  <li>access your start page</li>
  <li>access your blogging application (we choose <a href="https://withknown.com/">known</a> as default)</li>
</ul>

<p>And on the start page, on the blog section, in “advanced area”, you could access other blogging platforms from wordpress.mydomain.com, ghost.mydomain.com, static.mydomain.com and so on. And you’ll also have the possibility to switch your main domain to another one with a click.</p>

<h3 id="summary">Summary</h3>

<p>To sum up, the start page will have the following functionalities:</p>

<ul>
  <li>links to admin panels of applications</li>
  <li>choose the application that is on the main domain</li>
  <li>migrate to another hoster</li>
  <li>download a zip file of all your data</li>
  <li>submit a support ticket</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>As you can see, it’s still ongoing discussion :) We’d love to hear your feedback on that! But we believe that there is room to develop a good and simple user experience, and not another store/meta-software.</p>

<p>The idea is to start with this simple html page, and accept email tickets. And slowly, we’ll see the needs appearing. We can’t predict the future, but for IndieWeb hosting this is the experience we plan.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[We are CrowdFunding]]></title>
    <link href="https://indiehosters.net/blog/crowdfunding-go"/>
    <updated>2014-11-20T19:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://indiehosters.net/blog/crowdfunding-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="crowdfunding">CrowdFunding</h2>

<p>We just finished everything, and are ready to accept our first clients. We choose <a href="https://www.indiegogo.com/projects/indiehosters/x/9169969">Indiegogo</a> to pre-sale our service.</p>

<h3 id="you-can-check-our-video-here">You can check our video here:</h3>
<p><a href="http://igg.me/at/IndieHosters" target="_blank"><img src="/images/crowdfunding-video.png" /></a></p>

<h2 id="users-to-start-in-january">100 users to start in January</h2>

<p>We aim to get 100 clients, and start giving them IndieWeb applications from January. We believe it is a realistic goal. We already have 15 users in beta with wordpress. And we are polishing details for known. Then we’ll work on a small interface for the user choose his domain name. And we’ll be ready to send activation link by the end of January.</p>

<h2 id="beers-a-month">2 beers a month</h2>

<p>We did everything possible to offer you the cheapest we could. And we get to this price: 50€/domain/year. We really hope you’ll enjoy it and buy it for you and your relatives. And the big thing is whatever application we add in the future, you’ll have it, without paying more!</p>

<h2 id="migration-oriented">Migration Oriented</h2>

<p>We really believe that as a hosting network, we really make a difference by offering a “migration oriented” service. And hopefully hosting companies will adapt this philosophy little by little. We’re preparing a blog post about this subject to detail a bit more our plans on that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First funding]]></title>
    <link href="https://indiehosters.net/blog/first-funding"/>
    <updated>2014-11-13T19:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://indiehosters.net/blog/first-funding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="nlnet-grant">NLnet grant</h2>

<p>We are very happy to announce we secured our first funding! We receive a grant from the awesome <a href="https://nlnet.nl/">NLnet</a> foundation,
which will help us to add two important products. First of all, we will add <a href="https://withknown.com/">Known</a> as an alternative to WordPress.</p>

<p>Both Known and WordPress allow you to post on your own website, but whereas WordPress has a lot of plugins and the benefits of a huge global
user base, Known is more specialized in providing the latest technology from the <a href="http://indiewebcamp.com/">IndieWeb</a> community out of the box. So these will be our first
two products, for you to choose from.</p>

<p>Apart from that, we will add <a href="https://piwik.org/">Piwik</a> statistics, so you can always see how many people are visiting your internet domain,
on which days of the week you get the most visitors, and where they come from geographically. It’s a fun way to get some feedback after you
publish a post, and get some insight into your popularity.</p>

<h2 id="crowd-funding-on-thursday">Crowd-funding on Thursday!</h2>

<p>And we have some more exciting news! Today, we recorded the video for the crowd-funding campaign. We will edit it to a short version, and put
the crowd-funding campaign live on Thursday 20 November. So make sure you stay tuned and are ready to start being hosted with us!</p>

<p><a href="#cta" class="scrolly button">Stay tuned!</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[v0.2.0]]></title>
    <link href="https://indiehosters.net/blog/v0.2.0"/>
    <updated>2014-11-10T10:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://indiehosters.net/blog/v0.2.0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="version-020">Version 0.2.0</h2>

<p>For our 2nd beta version, we decided to work on the most popular blogging platform, wordpress. So from now on, we offer hosting for static sites, static sites with git, and wordpress. This change is quite a big change, we worked all the week on it.</p>

<h2 id="on-the-way-to-lamp">On the way to lamp</h2>

<p>And obviously, this work will be reused to host any kind of LAMP-based application, which is the most popular among FOSS projects.</p>

<p>Please, for more information, read the official <a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/indiehosters/releases/tag/0.2.0">release notes</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any comments, please feel free to share it with us!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CyberFoundation]]></title>
    <link href="https://indiehosters.net/blog/CyberFoundation"/>
    <updated>2014-11-04T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://indiehosters.net/blog/CyberFoundation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our soft launch was quite a success, 80 Facebook likes, 30 followers on Twitter, 50 newsletter subscriptions. We are really happy with that!</p>

<p>And with our first followers come our first concerns, and we believe this is important to answer doubts as soon as possible.</p>

<h4 id="on-facebookhttpswwwfacebookcompermalinkphpstoryfbid826221630755681id821708187873692commentid826861500691694offset0totalcomments5-magnus-wrote">On <a href="https://www.facebook.com/permalink.php?story_fbid=826221630755681&amp;id=821708187873692&amp;comment_id=826861500691694&amp;offset=0&amp;total_comments=5">Facebook</a>, Magnus wrote:</h4>

<p>“I love the idea, but how do you make sure, that you keep up with what you promise? After all, Couchsurfing promised to be non profit as well. Many years went by, people joined and when it became profitable they sold it all of a sudden.”</p>

<p>We understand this concern. And we would be as concerned as you in your position. That’s why we decided that IndieHosters should be a non profit cyber foundation. The role of this cyber foundation is to hold the “brand”, and “copyright” of every contributions that is made to it, like code, translations, or even donations. Then every IndieHoster (note the singular) is given the right to use the “brand” under some conditions (to be determined). And so every hoster is authorized to make a living from his work, and even profit, as long as his clients are aware.</p>

<p>For now, the cyber foundation doesn’t have any legal status in any nation state law system, but we are thinking about it. If you have some ideas, they are more than welcome! But basically, we have 2 documents that guide our work:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/documents/blob/master/cyberfoundation.md">CyberFoundation Status</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://degooglisons-internet.org/nav/html/charte.html">Charte from Framasoft</a></li>
</ul>

<p>We still have to translate this charte, and “officially” sign it.</p>

<p>As you can see, nothing is written in stone yet (French expression, sorry :) ), but we prepare the path. We also want to make sure, that you, the final user can contribute to it, and give your feedback before taking any decisions that could make a darker future..</p>

<p>But what is sure for now is that all code we write is AGPLv3 and every document is CC0, Public Domain.</p>

<p>And actually, we have a little doubt about the logo… Should it be copyright IndieHosters to make sure nobody can make bullshit with it, or should it be CC0 also?</p>

<p>So as you can see, we’ll try to be as transparent as possible. But if you have any questions, doubt, ideas, please, feel free to submit your changes on our <a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/">github account</a> or even, come to discuss things with us in our <a href="irc://chat.freenode.net/indiehosters">IRC channel</a>.</p>

<p>Image credit: http://choosealicense.com/</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Choice of server architecture]]></title>
    <link href="https://indiehosters.net/blog/version-0.1"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T17:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://indiehosters.net/blog/version-0.1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We finally started running the first two IndieHosters servers! This website is hosted on them, for instance. Version 0.1 of the server setup
is really quite basic. We try to avoid writing software as much as we can, and focus on hosting software built by other people.</p>

<p>We want to fill the gap between the free software product that says “We’re open source! You can host this on your own server!” and the
end-user, who often doesn’t want to (learn how to) host software on servers.</p>

<p>Hosting software on servers is often not very hard, at least not if you have some experience with using the Linux command-line.
Of course you get better and better over the years while you do it more often, but it’s mainly
a matter of following the instructions and recipes you’re given, applying a bit of common knowledge about how server software usually
organizes its configuration, processes and logs, and whenever something doesn’t work, search the forums for a solution.</p>

<h2 id="why-we-chose-a-generic-setup">Why we chose a generic setup</h2>

<p>We chose a Docker+systemd setup, for several reasons. First, we want to be able to offer any personal server application anybody may want.
This means we don’t want to commit to a specific personal server management tool. There are several projects that are working on graphical
user interfaces for server administration. They are like “meta software”: it’s software you install once, using the Linux command-line (or
it comes preinstalled on a physical device you buy), and after that it works like a graphical “app store”, where you can install other
software (sometimes called apps, plugins, etcetera) very easily (typically with one click on some “Install” icon).</p>

<p>Examples of such generic meta-software projects are:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://freedomboxfoundation.org/">FreedomBox</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://sandstorm.io">SandStorm</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://yunohost.org/">Y-U-No-Host</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://owncloud.org/">ownCloud</a> (where apps need to be PHP)</li>
  <li><a href="https://cozy.io/">CozyCloud</a> (where apps need to be NodeJS)</li>
</ul>

<p>We want to offer hosting for all these products, as well as for more specific server applications like postfix (email), Wordpress (blogging),
etcetera. We also want to help small and young free software projects to gain traction by offering hosting for them before the big hosting
companies do this.</p>

<h2 id="why-we-chose-docker">Why we chose Docker</h2>

<p>A lot of applications are available as LAMP applications, and by using Docker, we can easily offer all of these in a safe containerized
environment. If one of these applications contains a cross-site scripting or SQL injection vulnerability, then this should stay
entirely sandboxed,
and not affect the other applications the user runs. Docker provides this separation, as it is based on Linux containers. Also, Dockerfiles
provide an easy way to script the install steps of any Linux-based application in a reproducible way. For instance, this website has a
<a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/website/blob/source/Dockerfile">Dockerfile</a> which specifies exactly which version of grunt and jekyll you need
to build it from the markdown source, and because the build happens in a Docker container, someone building it on an Ubuntu laptop gets exactly
the same output as someone else building it on a Macbook.</p>

<p>By using Dockerfiles to describe exactly, and reproducibly, which application and configuration get installed on a server,
we will be able to easily offer hosting for hundreds of personal server setups, on a generic application-agnostic hosting stack.
Yet we are being very careful not to add a layer of software ourselves. We only
translate the build instructions of the upstream project to a Dockerfile, configure which port should be opened, and Docker does the rest.</p>

<p>Apart from containerization, and reproducible build instructions, another great feature are Docker volumes. As containers run, they have the
possibility to build up state: files like logs and user data change on the container’s internal filesystem, relative to their virgin state.
When you reset (i.e., stop, remove, and start) the container, this state is reset to the initial virgin state.</p>

<p>By mounting volumes from the host system into a Docker container for exactly the data you want to persist, this can be avoided. That we, we can
specify exactly what parts of the file system tree we consider “user data”, and which parts are either part of the image, or can be reset
to their virgin content from the image without affecting the application. This way, it is even possible to reset a container to its initial
state in between two http requests - as long as the place where the user sessions are stored is marked as data we want to mount in from the
host system, so that it is preserved across container resets.</p>

<h2 id="why-we-chose-systemd">Why we chose systemd</h2>

<p>We could of course use Docker directly from the command line. We could write some simple bash scripts that call the right Docker commands
for adding and removing processes on a server. However, there are a number of things that would be awkward to do from plain bash scripts.
For instance, only schedule a git pull for those websites which have been configured with the option to pull their content from some git
repository, and not for others. Or, making sure the webserver starts after the database server, and only if the database server was started
successfully.</p>

<p>For this, we use systemd. It handles the dependencies between different containers, organizes the specific Docker commands we want to be
executed to achieve different goals into its unit files syntax, and also replaces crontab. In line with the <a href="https://coreos.com/">CoreOS</a>
philosophy for running lean host systems for Docker hosting, we also use etcd to keep track of some system state (e.g. which application
is currently listening on which IP on the internal network), and confd templating to generate for instance the haproxy config file.</p>

<h2 id="version-01-now-available">Version 0.1 now available!</h2>

<p>We tagged a <a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/indiehosters/releases">version 0.1</a> in the repository containing our systemd unit files.
It contains basically two scripts: one
script for setting up a server with one default domain on there, and one scripts for adding another site to it. You can try it out
using the instructions in the README (using Vagrant is the easiest way to see the development version running on your laptop).</p>

<p>In this first initial version, the functionality is still very limited: it allows you to host several website over https on one IPv4
address using the SNI feature of haproxy. Each site can pull from a git repository every 10 minutes, or you can just ssh to the host
system to edit its html content. The backends run plain nginx in this version, so no php or mysql is available.</p>

<p>Additionally, a <a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/dockerfiles/blob/master/server-wide/postfix/Dockerfile">postfix-forwarder</a> is included
which will forward email to a secondary address.
See the <a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/indiehosters/tree/master/data/server-wide/postfix">data</a> folder of the IndieHosters repo for an example of how to configure it.</p>

<p>To get a feel for what such unit files look like, check out the <a href="https://github.com/indiehosters/indiehosters/blob/master/unit-files/wordpress%40.service">unit-files</a> folder.</p>

<p>Feedback welcome! We’re already making a lot of progress on version 0.2, which will include the necessary unit files for hosting LAMP applications like Wordpress and ownCloud.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello world!]]></title>
    <link href="https://indiehosters.net/communication/2014/10/27/hello-world.html"/>
    <updated>2014-10-27T08:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://indiehosters.net/communication/2014/10/27/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<div class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">RUN <span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">&quot;hello world&quot;</span></code></pre></div>

<p>We’re glad to present you our new project! And we hope you’re as glad as us ;)</p>

<p>Please, if you are interested by this excited adventure subscribe to our news letter and spread the word to your friends!</p>

<p>Let’s get excited!</p>

<p>See you soon for nice updates :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
